<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Impostor magnus, or The legerdemain of Richard Delamain now preacher in the city of Hereford. Being a narrative of his life and doctrine since his first coming into that county. Faithfully collected and published by one that will assert the truth of each particular. Yay.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Silas, 1624-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T553A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219169</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830683</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830683</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35136</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64240)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35136)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2081:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Impostor magnus, or The legerdemain of Richard Delamain now preacher in the city of Hereford. Being a narrative of his life and doctrine since his first coming into that county. Faithfully collected and published by one that will assert the truth of each particular. Yay.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Silas, 1624-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Silas Taylor.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Delamain, Richard, fl. 1654 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35136:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Impoſtor Magnus, OR The Legerdemain of Richard Delamain, NOW Preacher in the City of <hi>Hereford.</hi> BEING A Narrative of his life and Doctrine ſince his firſt coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that County. Faithfully collected and publiſhed by one that will aſſert the Truth of each particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>YAY.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jude,</hi> verſe <hi>11.</hi> and <hi>2 Pet. 2.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wo unto them, for they have gone in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and run greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam</hi> (the Son of <hi>Boſor,</hi> who loved the the wages of unrighteouſneſs) for reward: and periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the gainſaying of Core.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year, 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35136:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35136:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou takeſt no more pleaſure in the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Tract, then I did in the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, Ile aſſure thee thou ſhalt never be inebriated with any delight that it can afford thee: and perhaps you may wonder at this ſo large a collection of paſſages, perpetrated in the ſpace of four or five years; but your admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration will ceaſe, when you find that you never met (before this) with ſuch a deſigned piece of impoſture as this is: the whole tranſaction of his (ſcarce) quinquennial labor, being nothing but a continued ſeries, and cloſe reiterated conca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenation of deceits; ſo that what thou haſt here, is not a tithe of his actings which might have been gleaned up, nor the moiety of what I have heard and know: but what thou haſt is upon ſound grounds, and not ſurmiſes. This Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe is an Hiſtorical application, and partly explication of the Epiſtle written by Saint <hi>Jude,</hi> thoſe characters of Apoſtates, being his choice rules by which he ordered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, both in life and Doctrine. Here is not a confutation, but only a relation of his errors, and ſuccinct annotations upon them; which the ingenuous candid Reader may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large with his own obſervations; for if confutation had
<pb facs="tcp:35136:3"/>been intended, the neceſſary concluſions, probations, and reſponſes which would have followed, and muſt have been taken in, would have ſwelled this Book, far by much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the intentional bulk of it. And truly it had been no prudence to have alledged Scripture to him, that did deny the authority of it; our arguments muſt have riſen from the ſame Baſis as the Fathers and Antients uſed to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens; to perſwade them firſt of a God, &amp;c. what there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is here exhibited by way of animadverſion (Courteous Reader) is for thy uſe: if it ſhould make any impreſsion upon the heart of him that is the ſubject of our preſent and ſubſequent diſcourſe, I ſhall be joyful to hear of it, and joy <hi>Angelically at his converſion</hi> from a <hi>blaſphemous Saul</hi> to a <hi>preaching Paul;</hi> God <hi>being able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that theſe ſtones be made bread:</hi> but if he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all theſe ſhould continue reſolute and refractory in his wayes of evil, he will not miſs of a ſecond reproof; in the mean time (Reader) <hi>hold faſt the Faith once delivered, and be not carried about with divers and ſtrange Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.9.</note> for it is a good thing that the heart be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35136:3"/>
            <head>Impoſtor Magnus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have by ſearch endeavored to find ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for matter of ſublimity to run pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to this Hiſtory that I am now about to write, but find, that what <hi>Ebion, Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus, Samoſatenus, Sabellicus, Servetus,</hi> and others the antient Captains and Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders of this ſort of looſe Hereticks did embrace; nay, what <hi>Socinus</hi> the Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt of all the former, with the additional fermentations of his own brain, comes far ſhort of thoſe dangerous poſitions which our Impoſtor hath divulged and practiſed: for, as if to collect the ſigns and notes which the Spirit of God in the Scriptures hath given us to know, and by them to diſtinguiſh deluders from others, were the rules and Gnomon to direct him to ſhape his opinions and practiſe by, and the end and ſcope he endeavored at, and preſſed unto, it could ſcarce be otherwiſe, that he ſhould ſo point blank in himſelf accompliſh thoſe characters of Apoſtacy and Errors which are ſo flatly repugnant to the rule of life and Doctrine: And in the proſecution of this diſcovery, I ſhall be ſo ſparing of wreſting things beyond their intended weight and allowance, that I ingenuouſly confeſs and aſſure you, it is the higheſt <hi>Acme</hi> my deſires have aſpired unto, that there might have been a poſſibility of ſparing the whole, by ſome one
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35136:4"/>the ſmalleſt ſign and token of repentance and alteration; which being undiſcerned, and finding of how great uſe and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a publike and private good the unvailing of knavery is, eſpecially in ſuch, who by their callings ſhould be enſamples of good to others: I could not ſtill or quiet thoſe motions and ſuſurra's I had within me, till I had yielded to thoſe impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, and ſent this abroad for the benefit of the poor diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and over-ridden <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and all others that may find themſelves concerned in this diſcovery; whether it be for matter of eſtabliſhment or prevention: it being the ſecond volumn or Treatiſe of <hi>Machiavillian</hi> piety, and contains in it a <hi>Scheam</hi> or repreſentation of the manners, preachment and ſpeeches of that <hi>Grand Impoſtor, Richard Delamain,</hi> who with inticing words, gilding over his bitter pills of blaſphemy and error, hath done much miſchief in the neighbouring Counties; and if in this Tract the Reader ſhould be moleſted with the want of method, I beg his excuſe; for that I hope he will be pleaſed to conceive it no eaſie matter or task, to methodize Accidents, ſo much disjoyned in reference to place, perſons, times, and matter, as theſe enſuing are.</p>
            <p>He was the wicked Son of a good Father, from a Publican, turned a Phariſec, from one that ſate at the receipt of <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> to one that by a more indirect courſe accuſtomed himſelf to the receipt of gain; he uſed his apparel ſupermodiſh, powdering his long hair, but that the ſweet Gentleman was much behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him that brought him down, for his friendly advice of cutting it ſhorter, though in this ſhort cut it reached his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. He was perſwaded into the County of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and brought thither by Mr. <hi>M. H.</hi> of <hi>Webley,</hi> one that hath been a dogmatical <hi>Camaelion</hi> ever ſince the many coloured and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous headed <hi>Hydra</hi> of errors have been in faſhion; upon his firſt coming, which was in the year 1648. he was for a new light (though ſheltered in a dark lanthorn) brought to Mrs. <hi>V.</hi> a Gentlewoman of good family and reſpect, then living at <hi>Bred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardine</hi> in that Tract; where of the miniſter of the Pariſh leave being obtained for this our <hi>Hyperbolical Angel of Light to hold forth his gifts,</hi> he preached a Legal Sermon; full ſraughted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35136:4"/>with the greateſt Terrors of puniſhments and damnation, which was highly diſliked by the chiefeſt, who leaned very much to an Antinomian plauſibility (for in thoſe times this Country had not many baits to buſie themſelves about, and were ignorant of thoſe profound Soloeciſms, called new Notions: Independency, Presbyterie and Antinomianiſm in the leſſer volumn (not to the ſhaking off of duties) were the greateſt divertiſements then in practiſe) and truly the ill management of that miſtaken Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, had almoſt in the Threſhold cauſed him to have daſhed his foot to the ſtumbling and undoing of his hopes; for by this you may plainly perceive him a deſigned Temporizer, who for his gain could have become a downright Legaliſt, as well as a high flown Notioniſt; and in few words, to give you the print of his foot, by which you may imagine his ſtature; Gain was his Godlineſs, his Religion it was his God, his whole aym, and he reſolved (which by his leaving his ſmall place in the Cuſtom-houſe you may perceive) to obtain it <hi>per fas aut nefas,</hi> holding that <hi>Heterodoxal Maxim</hi> for his firſt point of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: <hi>dulcis odor lucri ex re qualibet;</hi> this enforced him to leave <hi>Bredwardine</hi> awhile, and go with <hi>M. H.</hi> to <hi>Webley,</hi> where by his means having inſinuated into the acquaintance of Mrs. <hi>K.</hi> one nearly related to that Family at <hi>Bredwardine,</hi> then living at a place about two miles from <hi>Webley,</hi> who out of her tender affection to good, imagining by his carriage and demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſome ſuperlative knowledge of Gods wayes; at leaſt ſome eminent ſanctity in himſelf, gave him countenance (and you may ſee here he firſt makes <hi>practiſe with women and widdows</hi>) where fiſhing with the bait of <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> and perceiving it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, proſecuted his fortune eagerly, making uſe of all advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages for <hi>leading of ſome Captive</hi> with his Tenents and abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and imagining his intereſt did much conſiſt in the getting into favor with the old Gentlewoman at <hi>Bredwardine,</hi> becauſe there was the beſt quarters, it being the nature of ſuch decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers much to mind their bellies; <hi>For what they naturally know as bruit beaſts, in thoſe things they corrupt themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 10.</note> and are the black <hi>ſpots</hi> in the <hi>feaſts of charity;</hi> and becauſe of the eminency of the place and Family, which by the means of theſe his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35136:5"/>acquaintance, he with ſome labor, at laſt, to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, atchieved; cauſing in ſome an admiration of his Doctrine which he <hi>now</hi> holds forth, I dare not ſay an approbation of it. I know it is Satans Maſter-peice to lay ſtumbling blocks before the feet of the Saints, and if it be poſsible, to cauſe ſuch as have been renowned for their profeſſion in the ſtricteſt wayes of Godlineſs, to be the <hi>Anteſignani,</hi> and chiefeſt abettors of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and error, to make ſuch <hi>whoſe light ſhould be ſet,</hi> as it <hi>were, on an hill:</hi> who ſhould by their lives and converſations be the flaming Beacons of <hi>Good works before men, that they ſeeing them, may glorifie our Father that is in Heaven;</hi> to cauſe them in a more eſpecial manner to be the greedy examples of falling, and ſucking in thoſe damnable poſitions of Chriſtian Lethargy. Here now <hi>this ungodly man having crept in unawares, ſpends</hi> his time betwixt the two Families; inſtructing them with his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved principles; and all ſuch as came unto them, either out of humanity, as to viſits, or out of the inſtigation of <hi>an itching ear to hear novelties,</hi> of which laſt ſort more eſpecially then others, ſome were caught, and did embrace Doctrines of the Devil: Tenents that now ſtink in the Noſethrils of ſome of his admirers, worſe then his breath doth to ſuch as approach him, he laboured to ſeduce; ſome of which I ſhall now give you a ſight of; though I know that errors (like oaths in telling ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) better concealed then repeated; yet becauſe he goe's on ſtill, making practiſe with deceits, deceiving and being deceived, aſpiring to eminent places, there to make ſhipwrack of Faith and a good conſcience; not only in himſelf, but to others, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting over the Miniſters, who are laborious and painful; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedling in civil affairs, in which he is nothing concerned; deſpiſing powers and authorities, and all this and much more under the cloak of Religion and conſcience; this is therefore to undeceive ſuch who by his fair perſwaſions may be drawn into the deceit of believing his lyes: for having, as in a draught or picture, ſeen his carriages and life; they may with little ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Logick, believe, that out of ſuch an impure polluted puddle, cannot proceed the limpid-living ſtreams of the water of Life; that whileſt himſelf is the very Epitome of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35136:5"/>and Herefie, and the abſtract of baſeneſs and leudneſs, he can in the mean time preach to others by his example the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Truth, holyneſs and ſincerity: <hi>That</hi> which he now buckled himſelf unto when he was received into favor at <hi>Bred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardine,</hi> was that common maxim which all Impoſtors uſe; <hi>to deſpiſe Dominions, and ſpeak evil of dignities,</hi> to decry all thoſe that may by any means be a <hi>remora</hi> in his proceedings; either by authority, Doctrine or diſputes; and to that end he declaims againſt the Miniſtry in general, as if the ſins and faylings of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, were annexed as inſeparable companions to the calling; even ſo, becauſe ſome have received poyſon in their meat, it were neceſſary or reaſonable we ſhould wholly deſiſt from the uſe of it; Here begins a loud invective againſt them, for many crimes which they are guilty of, and among the reſt, ſcorning them for their receiving Tithes, (though ſince he hath received them, and threatned trouble to thoſe that did not conform) and perſwades his Diſciples (to avoid the diſgrace and foyls, which elſe he and they were ſubject to in diſputes) that what he ſaid could not be underſtood be any, but ſuch who were under the the ſame diſpenſation as he was; <hi>(truly I think ſo too)</hi> and in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Maſter, you ſhould have ignorant ſilly women, tell men both learned and knowing: That they could not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thoſe high myſteries, becauſe of their carnality; and further tells them, that what was nonſence to all people out of his way, was the very ſenſe of the Spirit to him: by which he ſeemed to anticipate and confute all controverſies that might ariſe, and which was a very ſuccinct method of ſatisfying all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and doubts: and further, that what he delivered, though it were ſeemingly contradictory to the received truth, and though he could not prove it out of the written Word of God, yet it was to be received as the immediate dictate of the Spirit. He ſlighted and ſcorned at duties, as performed by ſuch who were in a lower form, and ſhould in time have greater light. And upon that place, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Behold I ſtand at the door and knock, if any man hear my voice and open the door, &amp;c.</hi> he held forth that the Ordinances <hi>of God</hi> were the door; that they do keep Chriſt at a diſtance from the Soul, and keep him in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35136:6"/>or dark to us; was not this a notable ingredient for his maſs of errors? not valuing the Spirits injunctions of praying continually, and rejoycing alwayes, exhorting, rebuking, &amp;c. in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon? Tells us that the Scriptures were but the mind of the Spirit in ſeveral adminiſtrations, and that there were ſeveral diſpenſations of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of <hi>Noah</hi> or <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Here is ſtrange ſtuff.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt.</p>
            <p>Of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Of fire burning up corruptions.</p>
            <p>Of Heaven or the Spirit, under which diſpenſation he then was. That the Scriptures were darkneſs; that the ſame Spirit dwelleth in us, that did in them that penned the Scriptures, which he proſecuted with ſtrange deductions and concluſions, never conſidering that teſtimonies are for clearing, not obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; that the Scriptures teſtifie of Chriſt, and do reveal him, that darkneſs doth not reveal things; it <hi>is light that makes manifeſt;</hi> that what is darkneſs, is in our underſtandings, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof we apprehend not the Scriptures, &amp;c. He further declared that we were taught of God immediately, and not of men, whereupon Mr. <hi>S.</hi> the School maſter of <hi>Hereford</hi> asked him, why he then took upon him to teach men; he anſwered, we do not teach, but only ſhew men (<hi>a learned diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi>) but that you may further ſee what he meant by Scriptures, or how in himſelf he did approve of them, being urged to back ſome Tenent or other of his with Scripture, he anſwered, <hi>That he did not much trouble himſelf with the Scripture.</hi> I need not apply it, for by this you may eaſily know his minde: but he proceeds and tells you, <hi>that that which is in us, is Chriſt, and he cannot ſin; that it was needleſs for a Saint to ask or make requeſt for any thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all was theirs, and they could want nothing;</hi> his phraſes were moſtly obſcured in Allegories (dreaming the whole Scripture was nothing elſe) and here he rumbles up ſtrange applications of old <hi>Adam</hi> and new <hi>Adam,</hi> light and darkneſs, liſe and death, Chriſt and Antichriſt, fleſh and Spirit, heaven and hell, <hi>Sion</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35136:6"/>
               <hi>Sinai,</hi> bright clouds and dark clouds; vails, diſpenſations, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, illuminations, living up, the Allegorical applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Grace, and glory: of Chriſts croſs, grave, burial, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and aſcention, with all his miracles and actions which were ſo miſuſed, miſapplyed, miſapprehended; ſo bumbaſted, ſqueized, wreſted, wrung and wreathed into a ſeeming ſenſe, that it would have puzzled a man of judgement, in the leaſt, to have apprehended them; <hi>Theſe are the clouds without water,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jude</hi> 12.</note> carried about of winds; trees, whoſe fruit withereth, without fruit, twice dead, plucked up by the roots;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> Theſe are empty wells with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out water, clouds that are hurried with a Tempeſt, to whom the miſt of darkneſs is reſerved for ever, for when they ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity, they allure them to error, while they promiſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty;</hi> but being now wrapt up in the admiration of his own non-ſence, it was asked him, how it was that he preached ſuch a Sermon of terrors, when he firſt came to <hi>Bredwardine?</hi> he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered (as his uſe was moſt commonly, with ſome miſapplyed place of Scripture) that he was perſwaded to it by Mr. <hi>Hill:</hi> but it was his liberty, and he could become all things to all men, to gain ſome: <hi>(he ſhould have ſaid for ſome gain)</hi> nevertheleſs ſome of his admirers were not ſo far deſerted, and led aſide, as totally to leave off duties, which by his example and preaching he alwayes held forth; for as he ſaid of his preaching that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or probation Sermon at <hi>Bredwardine,</hi> it was much againſt his inclination and Spirit, ſo was the uſe of any duties at evening or morning, either before or after meat,
<note place="margin">Jude.</note> 
               <hi>feeding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf without fear;</hi> and where he had liberty with ſome of his moſt abſolute proſelites, he laughed at them, ſaying, we perform duties, becauſe we look on God as a judge, and that it is the Spirit of bondage; yet at <hi>Bredwardine</hi> (which is obſervable) he was in a ſort conſtrained for keeping in with the old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, before and after meat to pretend a duty, which was nothing elſe but an impudent complement with God, not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the deſigned ends of thoſe duties, which were to pray for a bleſſing on the creatures, or give thanks for the reception of them; but his words were an odd pack of ſtuff,
<note place="margin">Delamains <hi>Grace at meals.</hi>
               </note> of non-ſence and blaſphemy; as theſe, <hi>O Lord, Thou art us, and we are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35136:7"/>Thee, Thou art in us and we in thee, Thou filleſt us with thy preſence, and we are full of thy fulneſs, Thou loveſt none but us, and we love none but thee; The creatures are thou; Thou art our light, our all, our all in all; To thee we give our all, we receive thee, we ſee thee, we delight in thee, and thou in us, to thee be glory, &amp;c.</hi> all this was not much to the purpoſe; but obſerve I pray, what a ſad object of Audacity is ſet before you; what ſtrange blaſphemy, to hold forth not only that every Chriſtian is God, but that every creature is God; may even the Devil himſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a creature: doth not he ſpin a fine thread, and winde up a skein or clew of ſtrange Corollaries? How can he be ſaid with this complement,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28, 29.</note> to come before God that is <hi>a conſuming fire, with reverence and Godly fear?</hi> or how doth he follow the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt, who for our pattern prayed for a bleſſing on the creatures before he uſed them; The Spirit enjoyning us <hi>in all things to make known our requeſts by ſupplications and prayers,</hi> and that <hi>continually:</hi> yet to what a degenerate impiety was this fellow grown, to confeſs him in words, but in deeds to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him? but if you will needs have duties, you muſt take them as he can afford them, for he tells you, that he hath waited many years and could never finde comfort while he uſed them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nemo repente fuit turpiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> Juven.</note> but leaving them, he found much; that before, he in dutyes ſound nothing but dryneſs and deadneſs, miſlaying that upon dutyes which was really the epileptical diſeaſe of his own Soul; and though at firſt in publick he concealed his venom and poyſon, yet in families he very freely traded with it; nay, he would preach one thing in publick and another in private; and in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate again deny what he had preached in publick, thus did he at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and truly he was engaged to it upon a force or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, elſe he could not maintain his poſition into practiſe; of becoming all things to all men to gain ſome, nor have been ſuffered to preach openly again; but that in the mean time you may ſee how he laid himſelf open to his proſelytes in theſe opinions: obſerve what one of them anſwered to an honeſt man of <hi>Ludlow,</hi> who at <hi>Leominſter</hi> demanded of him why <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamain,</hi> at the time of the publick exerciſe did preach in private, from whom he received this account, becauſe that he preached
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35136:7"/>there what was not fit to be preached or heard in publick, or if you will hear <hi>Delamains</hi> phraſe, it was becauſe as yet peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>could not bear his words and Doctrine.</hi> Thus did he frame himſelf to his work, in the proſecution of his deſign, of cauſing his Diſciples <hi>to ſit looſe from duties;</hi> becauſe we are frequently warned not to reſt on dutyes, he would have us leave them off. <hi>(That is a ſure way not to reſt on them indeed)</hi> which would open a Gate to all licentiouſneſs and prophanneſs; for if we were not bound to keep cloſe to a known rule, but left at liberty to follow the dictates of our own carnal appetites, to live and practiſe accordingly; if religion be ſome thing at large, not bounded or bonded, if it were only in this or that mans parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular liberty, (and in pretence) to become all things to all men, and this liberty to be explained by the reſpective owners and pretenders, then ſarewell to the very genuine ſenſe of the word <hi>Religion,</hi> and to all civil ſociety: to oppoſe them in their wicked wils, is an infringement of their liberty, and what can be elſe expected but a meer confuſion in Government and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, which is his longed for expectation, knowing the beſt fiſhing is in the muddieſt waters. But that I may not long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain you from a Sermon which I know you expect from our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Doctor, though as yet no Miniſter, for Crab-like he crawled backwards into theſe degrees, firſt a Preacher, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards (as he ſaith) ordained: I ſhall here preſent you with the Sceleron of one of his Sermons, which your imagination may help out, becauſe having ſuch rich conceits and far fetched no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties for the bare-heads, you may eaſily believe the covering was not much different; he believes not the litteral meaning of the Scripture, and therefore allegorizeth the three firſt verſes of the third Chapter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> whence he would have us note that the voice of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt crying in the wilderneſs, was the incomes of God into the wilderneſs of men.</p>
            <p>That thoſe Incomes of God,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Do make the aſcenſion of Chriſt within us; for Chriſt is dead and buried in the Soul till theſe Incomes come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are an exceeding weight of glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Are a Soul-ſaving glory.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:35136:8"/>
            <p n="4">4. Do ſet a Chriſtian on the ſhoulders of Chriſt, and then he may ſee compleatly.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Do bleſs the Soul.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Do deliver the Soul.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Do deaden all things to the Soul beſide God, ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Lord ſhall live there.</p>
            <p>(Then makes ſome ſhift, I know not how, to fall aboard with heaven, and tells you; (if you can underſtand him) for I confeſs I cannot.)</p>
            <p>That Heaven is an eſtate of God; nothing to be ſeen but God, and when thus I ſee God, then Heaven is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted.</p>
            <p>It contents a carnal Chriſtian to have Heaven without, and Chriſt without, &amp;c. but a ſpiritual Chriſtian looks for God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and heaven within.</p>
            <p>That there is no heaven but in the hearts of the Godly,
<note place="margin">Hogs-waſh.</note> nor hell but in the Hearts of the wicked, ſo that a man converted is hell changed into heaven.</p>
            <p>That Hell fire is nothing but the Spirits conſuming and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of Luſts, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now I hope for my repetition, I ſhall be excuſed from my Expoſition; and how would you have me expound that which I do not underſtand? I confeſs my ignorance, and will leave it to that generation, whom he imagines have a more glorious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, above Scriptures and Ordinances, or elſe to ſome that underſtand him, for he knew no other death, burial, or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention of Chriſt, nor heaven nor hell, but in the Soul, and how can you expect other from him?</p>
            <p>At other times, that he might ſhake and overturn the baſis and foundations <hi>of the Faith once delivered</hi> to his Diſciples, it was his uſe in his familiar and private converſe to low the ſeed of the Doctrine of the Seekers, from that place of Scripture, <hi>If ye are riſen with Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1.</note> ſeek the things that are above, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of his Father:</hi> making the whole intention and ſcope of the holy Spirit a notional Allegory; and holding out from thence, that in matters of Doctrine and Tenents there was nothing certain, eſpecially what was at any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35136:8"/>diſtance from his way; and that indeed was his practiſe with his Neophytes or Novices, to preach to them of ſhakings of Mount <hi>Slon</hi> and <hi>Sinai,</hi> (and what is written by the Author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi>) <hi>yet once more, and I ſhake not only the earth but the Heavens;</hi> you may eaſily interpret it his way; conſidering his deſign of beating Chriſtians off from duties, and his imagination of the locallity of heaven and earth, to be the ſouls and hearts of people; by this he endeavored to ſhake men from off their confidence in Scripture-rule or way, then putting them upon a ſeeking way; and to whom ſhould ſuch as were thus in their foundations ſhaken, have recourſe, but to ſuch as were able to ſhake them? and ſo as it was ſaid of the Phariſees of old, may be ſaid of our new one,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 23.</note> that <hi>they compaſs Sea and Land, to make one Proſelyte, and when he is made, they make him twofold more the childe of hell then themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he had tempered them to this paſs, they were ſit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to receive any impreſſion; and then he makes known to them, that there are nor either three or two perſons in the God-Head, and was much offended at the word Trinity, not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that it ſignified a <hi>Three;</hi> but it is the practiſe of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors to <hi>ſpeak evil of thoſe things which they know not;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude.</note> not minding what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>that there are three which bare record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy-Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7.</note> and theſe three are one;</hi> here is Trinity in Unity; but it is no marvel that he that ſpake ſo ſlightly of the God Head, ſhould deny the holy Trinity; he that dare, contrary to the plain words of the Scripture, which ſaith, <hi>God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all,</hi> belch out this blaſphemy, <hi>That God is dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and proſecute his horrid poſitions with pretended reaſon, and with telling his reprovers they wanted underſtanding; can you imagine he would ſtick at any eeror? yet favor him a little further, and he will tell you Chriſt is Faith, and Chriſt is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: That the world ſees Chriſt till the Spirit comes, and then the light of the Spirit puts out the eye of the world: That external adminiſtrations ſhall be ſhortly aboliſhed; That the body ſhall not riſe again, and that the humane nature of Chriſt did not riſe again; he may as well ſay ſo, as deny the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35136:9"/>hiſtory, contrary to thoſe places of Scripture, which affirm Chriſts reſurrection, and plainly ſay that <hi>Chriſt is now riſen from the dead, and become the firſt fruits of thoſe that ſlept;</hi> and thoſe many undenyable arguments wherewith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſyllogize the <hi>Corinthians</hi> into an underſtanding and belief of the reſurrection,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> in the fifteenth Chapter of his firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle.</p>
            <p>He commends to their readings the inexplicable Treatiſes of Chimital Divinity, written by the <hi>German</hi> Doctor <hi>Behmen,</hi> therein admiring what neither Writer, Reader, or Hearer could underſtand or make ſenſe of; much applauding <hi>his Tincture, his Ignis fatuus,</hi> and <hi>Turba magna; (Reader, theſe were all, as ſimple as they ſtand here, terms of Divinity)</hi> there was another ſuch-piece of extaſied non-ſenſe, written by a melancholly Frier or Brother of the Teutonick order, and ſmelt extreamly of the ingredients of <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Rheniſh</hi> wine, (whoſe name I have forgot) who was in great veneration among them: ſo were alſo Mr. <hi>Colliers</hi> works, and truly with <hi>Randalphs</hi> diſcreet tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations, ſuch opinioniſts might have been furniſhed with a ſmall library of ſuch Books, whoſe very names would have troubled you, more then the wooden horſe did the <hi>Trojans:</hi> but that you may not be troubled with the reading of them, you ſhall have them epitomized in two words, <hi>They were profound non-ſenſe:</hi> yet our Impoſtor would have had ready an anſwer for you, and ſo had his Diſciples alſo; <hi>They were non ſence to you, becauſe you cannot underſtand them,</hi> and what they could not expreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the interpretation, that they did admire, hoping ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other they ſhould with waiting have it revealed unto them; and they could conceive ſomething more a great deal then they could utter, but the women they underſtood it as faſt as could be: and their admirations were at their own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: even ſo do the Turks admire Ideots, thinking they have ſomething extraordinary of God in them, becauſe they underſtand them not. This jigg that our Impoſtor uſed, was not the armor of good lives, but only the canva-painted-ſtalking horſe of deluſion.</p>
            <p>One Sabbath day he urged from theſe words in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35136:9"/>For to him that is joyned to all the living, there is hope:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.4.</note> for a living dog, is better then a dead Lyon.</hi> Where only naming the latter part of the verſe, without looking or conſidering the firſt, either through wilfulneſs or negligence, he declared and inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon it, that the living dog was Chriſt Jeſus, and the dead Lyon were Believers, and how ſweetly this indign expoſition may ſerve for his notional frenzy, let any one judge; but this I have been aſſured, that when he had finiſhed his half hours fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, being reproved for ſuch an interpretation or application, this reproof being before the moſt and chiefeſt of his Auditors, with a requeſt to him to read the foregoing verſes, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent part of that verſe, by which he might plainly have ſeen his miſtake (the wiſe King ſpeaking there of life and death) he made this publick replication, firſt by an interrogation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his reprover did hear him give that interpretation of it? to which having received a poſitive affirmation, becauſe he had wrote it after him; he then made this reply, that his reprover did not hear with ſpiritual ears: that though that interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were falſe to his reprover, yet it was true to him; and ſo being netled and in paſſion, flung out of the room: which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and carriage was ſomewhat diſreliſhed by ſome of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, and excuſed <hi>by mans frailty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what he meant by the two contrarieties of Truth and falſhood, you may plainly-ſee by another paſſage that was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by him, much about that time; for having paced the ground-work of the ruined Caſtle of <hi>Snowdle,</hi> in the gilden val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, and making a draught of the ground-lines upon a piece of paper, ſeigning a ſmall ſcale to it for the dimenſion, which how unlike a Mathematicians work it was, I will not now declare, though if he had had any ingenuity he might have had a little more inſight in the Mathematicks from his Father, who had ſome skill in them; he ſuperſcribed the Scale with theſe words, <hi>Scala paſsium;</hi> and being before ſome of his admirers, reproved for falſe Latine; he replyed, that though it was falſe Latine to his reprover, yet it was true to himſelf; by which you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Blades opinion of <hi>true</hi> and <hi>falſe:</hi> but to his Doctrine; the Scripture ſaith otherwiſe of ambiguities, That there is but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35136:10"/>
               <hi>one</hi> Faith,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>one</hi> Baptiſm, <hi>one Truth, one Way,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> Lord Jeſus, and that <hi>no Scripture is of a private interpretation;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he ſaith it may be falſe to one, and true to another: <hi>this is rare, but real.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon an extraordinary convention of friends at <hi>Bredwardine,</hi> in the preſence of Colonel <hi>Taylor,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tombes,</hi> Captain <hi>Taylor,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bedwell,</hi> Mr. <hi>Swayn</hi> and others, he made ſhift in his arguing (which was carried on by him with ſuch an elated arrogance and impudent ſcornfulneſs of the Miniſters that were there) to pronounce in plain words, without welt or guard; That him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, was God. <hi>(Replic.)</hi> God is eſſentially God, are you eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially God? <hi>Delamain</hi> anſwered: I am God, as God is God. <hi>(Replic.)</hi> If you are God, then we muſt worſhip you; Which he preſently went about to confirm with Scripture; unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably wreſting and applying to himſelf that text, and ſaying, it is written,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.23.</note> 
               <hi>Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers, and Queens your nurſing Mothers, they ſhall bow down unto thee, with their face towards the earth.</hi> Yet at the ſame time declared himſelf to be a beaſt, and that God did oftentimes ſpeak through ſuch beaſts; which they granted: for to ſtrengthen his poſition, it was there acknowledged that God had ſpake through <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſs. What is there wanting now to the Completion of the Characters of Deceivers; <hi>Doth he not deny the only Lord, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt? Doth he not bring in damnable Hereſies? Even denying the Lord that bought us, bringing upon himſelf ſwiſt deſſtruction?</hi> Is he not <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> in <hi>exalting himſelf above all that is called God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</note> or <hi>that is worſhipped as God, ſitting in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God?</hi> Is not this man fit now to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with double Benefices, and the care of Souls? being ſuch a blaſphemous novice, wreſting the Scriptures unto <hi>the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of himſelf,</hi> and <hi>of thoſe that hear him and follow him;</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing learning, and learned men, becauſe ſuch are able to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom and unvail his ſetches; and yet forſooth himſelf would be thought a Scholar, owning himſelf of the Univerſity of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi> and being demanded by Mr. <hi>S.</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Worceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> of what Colledge he was, he anſwered him, of <hi>Emanuel</hi> Colledge: <hi>oportet mendacem eſſe memorem,</hi> here his friend the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35136:10"/>Devil, did not readily aſſiſt him, but left him to ſhift for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which how poorly he did, I need not tell you: for though <hi>Emanuel</hi> be applicatory to his notions, yet I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not how <hi>Oxford</hi> is.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Wyebridge</hi> houſe in <hi>Hereford,</hi> being diſcipling his auditors to a very great height of whimſy; he pointing to a ſilver Beer-Bowl ſtanding on the Table, ſaid, that <hi>that was God to him:</hi> (I believe he ſpake truth before he was aware of it) yet his baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was great, in comparing the great Creator of Heaven and Earth, to vile, contemptible and corruptible things, as ſilver and Gold: Theſe blaſphemies are not the tenth nor the hundredth part of what he hath practiſed his profane mouth withall; yet enough to ſtartle any one from having either belief or confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in him, or in his Doctrine; ſtill he proceeds gaping <hi>after filthy lucre,</hi> and plots now to get into ſome publike place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knew all people would in a ſhort time grow weary of him: for that by his familiſtical carriages he ſeemed to diſcover his rotten heart, plainly diſcovering he turned the Grace of God into wantonneſs,
<note place="margin">Jude.</note> manifeſting that he is one of thoſe <hi>filthy dreamers that defile the fleſh,</hi> and <hi>who walk after their own ungodly luſts;</hi> he began to diſtill by circumlocutions, ſuch things that but to name were a ſhame; community of goods and women, was a thing very conſiſtent to his zealous Breeches, ſaying <hi>that he had a propriety in another mans wife, as alſo in his goods;</hi> this feared not he openly to avow before divers Gentlemen, Miniſters, and others at <hi>Bredwardine,</hi> which how like his future carriages it was, and how neceſſary for his practiſe, you ſhall hear anon.</p>
            <p>He now practiſes his deceits at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> where for his Doctrine and life after ſome ſmall time, he was juſtly ſpued out; the abominations of which I ſhall reſerve for a particular Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, becauſe I would not have this of <hi>Hereford-ſhire</hi> ſwell too big; that of <hi>Worceſter</hi> having another variety of blaſphemy and luſt in it.</p>
            <p>And being caſt out there, he would try his fortune with Lieutenant Colonel <hi>VVroth Rogers,</hi> Governor of the Caſtle of <hi>Hereford,</hi> becauſe he was reſolved he would try all means of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35136:11"/>himſelf into ſome place for gain; and procuring him ſelf into an intimacy with the ſaid Governor, (as it is no hard matter for any flatterer or fawner) the Governor was reſolved to get him into places and preferment; firſt then he gets into the great Guns of the Caſtle; and for my part I ſhould have thought he would have fitted the Morter piece for a ſhell, becauſe of his emptineſs; and for a Granado alſo, for I believe there is not a greater incendiary happened into civil ſociety; but now he pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes the Mathematicks, and meaſures out his ware by the length of his gilded hilted Rapier, ſtrutting in a Souldier-like poſture, for a ſcurvy Matroſs of the Caſtle, like a Crow in a Gutter; owning himſelf a Mathematician, and declaring his greateſt learning conſiſted in the knowledge of the Mathematicks; <hi>(but that was by his favor in taking the dimenſions and length of men and womens feet, ſo as he might from a miſerable Preacher, turn a Mathematical paraſite)</hi> but for his skill, I have reaſon to believe, he was not guilty of much, nor ſo much as to make him a Gunner, yet here he ſtayes, diſparting the ſmall fire-Drakes of his erroneous dreggs, and begins with much devotion to leave his old courſes of blaſphemy, becauſe they had left him; and people began to grow weary of that courſe of courſe ware.</p>
            <p>But being ſolicitous for his gain: he lacks nothing but a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial man that may have the honor to convert him, and ſo himſelf become his Proſelyte; and that nothing may be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the compleating of this ridiculous Scene, Enter Major General <hi>Harriſon,</hi> he who did but look upon him, and by his phyſiognomy aſſured us of his converſion, and further (nay we muſt believe it) that he had made his recantation; and it may be better believe it, then go to diſprove it: for if his recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation were called to publick Teſt, and ſeriouſly ſearched after, it would be much like the ſtory of <hi>Enoch</hi> his Pillars, on which were wrote many ſtrange things, but all waſhed away with the Deluge, and ſo it muſt be returned with a <hi>non eſt inventum;</hi> and prove at leaſt to be but a Greek <hi>Ogygies,</hi> an inviſible record; but however this ſuperficial converſion ſerved his turn, he haſtens to get a Church, and being a Gunner, almoſt at the firſt firing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35136:11"/>caught one alive; and how he hath bred it up to his hands, and out of it framed a thing to his own ends, you may perceive by the ſequel: He now lives at <hi>Nathan Cogans,</hi> where he ſhews himſelf more effectionate to Mr. <hi>Cogans</hi> wife, then to his own child when it dyed <hi>(being void of natural affection to it);</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.31.</note> for Mrs. <hi>Cogan</hi> being very much troubled with Convulſion fits, he in thoſe fits embraced her, kiſt her, and ſhewed very much love to her; yet having entred into a Church way, knowing his proneneſs to fly out, he told his Church he would do nothing without their approbation now, and therefore deſires they would give their conſent to take a wife, naming her whom he ſince hath married, being a ſervant maid to Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Rogers</hi> his wife, and further makes it his requeſt, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it would be very <hi>convenient</hi> for his wife to have a maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant, that they would grant him leave to take a hired ſervant from her Miſtriſs, which they poor wretches did eaſily grant to him; and ſo he ſeduced <hi>Jane South</hi> of <hi>Greendon</hi> her maide from her, whom ſhe had long kept and bred: he had been tamper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with her, when as a gueſt he was entertained in <hi>Jane South</hi> her houſe, where betwixt himſelf, this ſervant and <hi>Jinny Clare,</hi> there was ſuch pretty night paſtimes, of warming of pillows, and other midnight works, that he began ſhrewdly to be ſuſpected there, if not detected, at leaſtwiſe much diſreliſhed; making good what the Apoſtle warns us of:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>spots and blemiſhes they are, ſporting themſelves with their own deceivings, while they feaſt with you, having eyes full of adultery, and that cannot ceaſe from ſin, beguiling unſtable ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that you may alſo ſee of what generation of people his Church conſiſts, following the example of their Paſtor, (though I am confident many of them are truly Godly, and ſuch ſeeing his miſdemeanors and wickedneſſes, do daily deſert him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcovered, will all leave him) but ſuch who pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their trade of ſinning, will glory in their Cloak, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting to make Religion a covert for their baſeneſs, of which ſort are two of his Church, <hi>Iohn Davis</hi> a Taylor, and <hi>Anne Madox</hi> a School-miſtreſs, both neer neighbors at <hi>Areſland</hi> in this County of <hi>Hereford:</hi> this <hi>Iohn Davis</hi> was husband to a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35136:12"/>woman ſimply honeſt, who perſwaded his wife to permit <hi>Anne Madox</hi> to lye with them (her houſe being cloſe by) there they lye all night, and in the morning very early, <hi>Davis</hi> perſwades his wife to riſe and go to the Bake-houſe, for to diſpatch her affairs there; which ſhe (poor woman) very readily conſented unto; and left her husband and <hi>Anne Madox</hi> faſt aſleep toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; (nay further, you muſt believe that there they lay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out waking four hours together, or you ſhall be none of <hi>Dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi> Church) the wife knowing no hurt in the thing, divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it at the Bake-houſe to her neighbors, by which means it came ſo publick, and was ſo plain, that divers and the wife having her eyes opened, complained of it, the witneſſes proved it, notwithſtanding the Governor of <hi>Hereford</hi> his threatning of them, to fine them <hi>one hundred pounds;</hi> yet I ſay it was proved; now were the Governor and <hi>Delamain</hi> put to their ſhifts, to cover this ſpiritual wantonneſs; and truly it was a poor ſhift; for <hi>Iſaac We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> one of the proſecutors and witneſſes, being ſeduced by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> promiſes or threats, pretends, that as he was going in the proſecution of this buſineſs, he had ſeen in a viſion at <hi>Canon-peon,</hi> an Angel or Spirit, who told him, that although <hi>Iohn Davis</hi> and <hi>Anne Madox</hi> lay commonly together, yet they did not ſo much as kiſs one another, &amp;c. I hope you cannot chuſe but believe it, with miracle and all: theſe are, or lately were of <hi>Delamains</hi> Church, to the pablick ſhame and reproach of all congregated and gathered Churches in the Nation: <hi>but here it is, like Prieſt, like people.</hi> He hath alſo perſwaded this his Church, under the Title of <hi>we the Godly,</hi> to ſet their hands to papers, being certificates againſt ſome honeſt man or other that took notice of his villanies; which certificates they had not the liberty either to ſee, read, or know the ſubſtance of; but aſſured them that they were for the glory of God, and good of the Godly.</p>
            <p>During this time, our luſty Prieſt had but a foot Souldiers pay and a Canoniers, and he found it was not ſufficient; he was provided therefore by the <hi>Governor,</hi> of many other pretty miſſets and portions, for if thoſe two former would not do, he ſhall be a Muſter-maſter and pay-maſter, a Clerk or Trooper
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35136:12"/>in the County Troop; ſo that you may now behold him a double beneficed <hi>Mirmidon,</hi> having a great command both in horſe and foot; and truly there was great <hi>occaſion</hi> for it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a Godly man, and it was good to engage ſuch an one to our party, for that the Scots were coming towards <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> for which pay he kept intelligence with our <hi>dear Brother</hi> Colonel <hi>Iames,</hi> (one of Major General <hi>Harriſons</hi> valiant Croneys) and let a furious party on <hi>Malvern</hi> hills know that the Governor of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> Colonel <hi>James,</hi> was fixedly reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in his Canon proof armor, with his ſword out drawn, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo fearful, and with that fear beſide himſelf, that he could not ſtir; for attempting to have run away on the other ſide <hi>Severn,</hi> he found the Draw-bridge ſo ſtrongly faſtned, that hindred his deſign, and put him into a great amazement, and can you blame him? for Ile aſſure you, the Scots were within 15 or 16 miles, and how ugly the <hi>High-Landers</hi> looked in their plades, would have amazed any one that could not have preached them away: but at that very place our <hi>Heroe</hi> offered the <hi>Hereford</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, which Colonel <hi>Iames</hi> refuſed, and I think wiſely too; for he had men enough to run away withal.</p>
            <p>But theſe military places were not the things aymed at, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were ſubject to mutation; therefore it would do well to have ſomething that might bring in an annual gain; and truly the Militia of the County of <hi>Hereford,</hi> having reſolved themſelves into a Committee, upon ſerious deliberation, for his military atchievements, gave him the three pariſhes of <hi>Ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaſtree,</hi> little <hi>Hereford,</hi> and <hi>Longtown;</hi> but becauſe he could not receive Tithes in point of tenderneſs of conſcience, He procures Mrs. <hi>W.</hi> of <hi>Aymonaſtree</hi> to receive them, and give him the money, ſhe being his dry nurſe, and fed him with ſilver ſpoons, for his ſpiritual food to her, and for making her Son (a pretty boy) a Juſtice of the peace for the County, which was a place, with <hi>Hereford</hi> Husbandry, that will <hi>(for all your laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing)</hi> bring in meat, drink, and clothes.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Longtown,</hi> he had ſome dealing with an honeſt Taylor, with his party coloured beard, who not pleaſuring him with an expected ſumme, ſeized on his horſe, or threatned to ſeize on
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35136:13"/>him; but whether he did, or only threatned, he by it forced the poor man to condeſcend to his demands, notwithſtanding he ſhewed him how he had been at about thirty ſhillings charges; which he would by no means allow the man; according to what S. <hi>Peter</hi> foretels of ſuch: <hi>That through covetuouſneſs, they with feigned words ſhall make merchandize of you,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3.</note> whoſe judgement lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greth not, and their damnation ſlumbreth not:</hi> but this that he received was not Tithes, it was but Tithe-money: and what made alſo much for him, was the conveniency of the Pariſhes together, that ſo having undertaken the cure, with ſuch facility he might provide for them; I believe there was not one of them within 8 miles of the other, and ſome further diſtant: but not content with theſe; he <hi>exerciſeth his heart with covetous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes,
<note place="margin">Jude.</note> running greedily after the way of</hi> Balaam <hi>for reward:</hi> and labors to get added to theſe, the Pariſh of <hi>Pembridge,</hi> by <hi>the wages of iniquity,</hi> promiſing one <hi>Rich. Byrd</hi> one hundred pounds, if he would bring ſufficient matter to out the incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, and proſecutes the deſign vigorouſly, having already by his truſt to his potent friends, ſwallowed it, yet miſſed of it: this practiſe up and down he continued till the year 1652. when by the aſſiſtance of his party and friends, he procures himſelf, into the room of Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> into the Minſter Church of <hi>Hereford,</hi> (one that was a Godly ſincere plain dealing man, but diſturbed in his Pulpit by the Souldiers of the Garriſon, and frighted away) to which place the Parliament had ſettled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to three Miniſters, 150. pounds a year on each; now you would think that he ſhould have had enough, having wrigled himſelf into this place; but ſuch was his greedineſs of filthy lucre, that with this he keeps the other Pariſhes, till he was ſhamed out of them: yet notwithſtanding the Governor (his great friend) being called up to the new Parliament (keeping himſelf all that time in the Government of the Caſtle of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>) improves his intereſt with his friends, helping him not only to his Fathers arrears, but alſo to the Minſters Salary, for that very time as he had kept the forenamed Pariſhes in his own hands (and this alſo by the Governors knowledge, by which you perceive they prefer their own private intereſt before the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35136:13"/>publick) and not being able to endure to have but one employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or benefice, by the ſame means he was got into the maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Hoſpital, and <hi>Thompſons</hi> gift; in which two chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table places, he behaved himſelf ſo unworthily, that he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the common talk and curſe of the poor; he rayles up an antient, undenyable, and unqueſtionable way, for watering in the Caſtle ditch to the City: inſtead of giving to ten or twelve poor people cloth for cloathes, according to their uſe, at half a crown a yard, he ſearched over all the City, and found a parcel of cloth at ſixteen pence a yard, which he bought, and wherewith he cloathed them; ſo you may perceive he will rob the Spittle, rather then miſs of his purpoſe for gain; the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor after procures an Order for Mr. <hi>Voyle,</hi> one of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and <hi>Delamain,</hi> to attend the ſervice of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the City; which when once <hi>Delamain</hi> had got, he uſurped the principal place, <hi>(the Minſter)</hi> to himſelf, though ſecond in the order; then what work did he make with the reſt of the miniſters, forbidding them to preach; charging the Sextons of the Churches, not to open the doors or ring a Bell without his permiſsion; ſcarce giving way to Mr. <hi>Primroſe</hi> to give his Pariſh of S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> notice of the Order, or take his leave of thoſe people to whom he had preached many years: laboured to hinder Mr. <hi>Low</hi> from preaching at one of the Churches that day on which he had accuſtomed to ſtay in the City for breaking of bread. And whereas for the ſuperviſing the raparations of the Minſter, it was referred by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for plundred Miniſters, to Captain <hi>Taylor,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Seaborn:</hi> becauſe he found not Captain <hi>Taylor</hi> at all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to comply with his deſigned plots, he and the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor cauſes <hi>Seaborn</hi> to certifie an untruth to the Committee, that Captain <hi>Taylor</hi> had Country imployments, and ſo could not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this work, upon which were ordered an addition of the Governor and Captain <hi>Maſon;</hi> whereas the quarrel was, that Captain <hi>Taylor</hi> would have done that work <hi>gratis,</hi> and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor was privy to it alſo, which might have been prejudicial to <hi>Delamains</hi> deſigns, for he was reſolved nothing ſhould ſcape him, but he would have a finger in it, and he intended to flay
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35136:14"/>flints, rather then miſs of the ſweetneſs of getting; and if Captain <hi>Taylor</hi> had ſtayed in equal truſt, how could <hi>Seaborn,</hi> that ſold ſo many Bells for this work, have gone on ſo merrily with his gettings, or get ſo much as to become a Purchaſer; or how could they have given <hi>Delamain</hi> the power of ſuperviſing beſides their order, they themſelves being but Deputies? which imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (as we have lately named them unto you) cauſed him to ſurceaſe the Tueſdays Lecture at the Minſter; which for many years had been continued, for being ſpoken unto to continue them, he anſwered, that the buſineſs of Saint <hi>Ethelberts</hi> Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital did take up ſo much of his time, that he could not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, by which means it hath been long diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued.</p>
            <p>That was not the only trouble neither, his ſurveying the works of the Minſter, of which he reckons himſelf parochial Paſtor, <hi>(but that muſt then be by ſome inviſible order)</hi> and where he orders all things to his own whimſical will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the referrees being but ſervants to his orders; and there makes ſo many baubles and fooleries, with ſo great an expence of the Pariſh money, that it is admirable: ſhews his ſpite and malice againſt all to whom he was diſaffected, turns them out of their ſeats, falls upon Colonel <hi>Birches</hi> ſeat, pulls it down, takes away and converts the materials to other purpoſes, breaks open the lock of Captain <hi>Taylors</hi> ſeat door, and alters it, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring him the key, proclaims in his Pulpit, that thoſe that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſeats muſt come to him, turns out the Sextons, cauſeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a total alteration in the ſeats and alleys of the Church, painting figures and letters upon the doors of the ſeats, and to ſhew his skill in the Mathematicks, beſtows the ſign <hi>Taurus,</hi> with the horns towards the Pulpit, upon the Governors ſeat; <hi>Gemini</hi> upon the Maior and Aldermens; <hi>Aries</hi> upon the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Caſtle, and the Governors attendants; which learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he got out of an <hi>Ephemeris</hi> and diſcourſe of the elevation of the Pole, long ſince imagined by Sir <hi>Thomas de Cantelupo,</hi> who lay intombed in <hi>Herefond,</hi> and whoſe <hi>fountian</hi> or <hi>jitteau</hi> hath been long immerged, under the <hi>watery region</hi> of the <hi>Caſtle ſink;</hi> and thus doth he abuſe his chiefeſt friends, rather then
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35136:14"/>not innure himſelf to his reſolved practiſe and trade of abuſes; his ſqueazy ſtomack hath throughly digeſted Tythes, and the calling of the Miniſtry now: and one would think him a much altered man, but that being taxed for his former opinions and courſe of life, he declares, <hi>he is the ſame man ſtill;</hi> and this he hath done lately, which alſo compared with ſome late Socinian flaſhes, will make the matter clear and indubitable, and are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to the diligent obſervers.</p>
            <p>On <hi>July</hi> 25. 1653. at <hi>Alhallows</hi> in the City of <hi>Hereford,</hi> ſpeaking of changes wrought in a man at his converſion, ſaid, that then his Soul is made a Spirit; <hi>(this is pretty)</hi> further alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. to prove the <hi>gathering together into one perſon Chriſt;</hi> he expounded all things in heaven to be God, and all things upon earth, Man, (<hi>Galilaeus</hi> and <hi>Copernicus their conceits were toyes to theſe knick knacks</hi>) and adds, that wicked men can caſt out Devils, but not <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> the Prince of Devils, out of the 7. of <hi>Matth.</hi> it is againſt his liberty to preach the Tueſdays Lectures, but not to preach funeral Sermons to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the dead, and pray over them, to ſing over them in the Church, and the ſame Pſalm as heretofore in Cathedrals was authematically uſed, and after all threaten the Sextons for the mourning-borrowed-Pulpit-cloath, as his fee: this was his liberty: ſo alſo was a Chriſtmaſs Sermon out of Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> upon the text, <hi>Great is the myſterie of Godlineſs, Chriſt manifeſt in the fleſh;</hi> but not being able to read or pronounce true Latine, he tells you, <hi>hoc eſt magnum myſterium quae, &amp;c.</hi> and though he hath taken up this Trade, his ſtudies are not very ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate, which in all reaſon would have concerned him; but who more bold then blinde <hi>Bayard?</hi> not truſting to his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, he commonly makes uſe of ſome good Author or other for his Sermons, as the forenamed Biſhop <hi>Andrews, Downam, Dyke;</hi> nay, <hi>Cauſinus</hi> and <hi>Drexelius</hi> the Jeſuites muſt not ſcape him, and yet though he hath a great memory <hi>(which is his all)</hi> he hath not as yet attained to the faculty to remember Latine or Greek well, but out of ſome Author or other, rimes up a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or Latine chime, and tells us that three things are inſeparable companions, <hi>ingentia beneficia, ingentia peccata, &amp; ingentiae
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35136:15"/>poena;</hi> he preacheth downright, that no one ought to preach, but ſuch as have a call both from God and men, and the call from men to be by the Officers of the Church, viſibly, and not long after confutes himſelf again; but tis his liberty: he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares he is ordained: a huge altered man; and it may be ſo; <hi>(for in imitation of it, he hath the happineſs himſelf to do many things hand over head.)</hi> but I call him altered and reformed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath heretofore publickly declared in theſe words, <hi>I am no Miniſter, nor never will be, I know no cauſe why any man ſhould:</hi> but to our ſtory, he doth not only ſay himſelf or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, but ſent to <hi>London Iohn Garnons</hi> to be ordained for his leavings at little <hi>Hereford,</hi> becauſe he himſelf the father had got great <hi>Hereford;</hi> this is he whom he calls his Son <hi>Timothy;</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Oneſimus</hi> in the firſt vellom, (volumn I ſhould have ſaid;) becauſe of his running away from his maſter, and leaving his trade of a Glover, to draw on the Kid-skin of diſſimulation, by a ſeeming care and zeal of converſion of pelts: this young boy he ſent to be ordained, that ſo he might have an eaſier trade to live on, then by ſtitching: and can you blame him, for fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing this counſel; being not for his liberty to ſtay with his maſter, working on the week dayes, writing Sermons on the Lords dayes, and then to repeat them at night: Oh! this was irkſom and tireſom to his tender griſtles; but becauſe that the Law may not proceed againſt him, the Governor of the Caſtle muſt lift him a Souldier there, and keep him to his ſewing till he become fit for the Miniſtry: Here is brave juggle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, brave Garriſon, brave Governor, brave Prieſts, brave people, brave maintainers of Law, Liberty and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety.</p>
            <p>But this Gentleman, <hi>John Garnons,</hi> Glover, may have another character, for I have ſeen his depoſitions at <hi>Haberdaſhers</hi> Hall againſt Captain <hi>Taylor,</hi> in which he followed his Father <hi>Dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> in the lye and ſlander of alaruming the Caſtle of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> with a muſick-meeting; only our buſineſs is principally with <hi>Delamain</hi> at preſent.</p>
            <p>You might now think that our deceiver and <hi>familiſm</hi> had ſhaken hands and parted, but that you have heard that he doth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35136:15"/>declare to divers, that <hi>he is the ſame man ſtill:</hi> elſe would he have labored to have ſet thoſe in the right path, whom he hath ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and have at leaſt made publick his leaving his own erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wayes: and how ſadly this ſhews, let any Chriſtian judge, that thoſe whom he hath infected with his leproſie and ſcurf of hereſie; thoſe who by his means have left the <hi>good old wayes</hi> and <hi>pathes,</hi> wherein they walked, in ſpight of all the ſcorns and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſions of the world; thoſe that for the teſtimony of a good conſcience have ſuffered from friends and enemies, from relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and acquaintance; that they ſhould lye ſleeping with the ſoporiferous <hi>opium</hi> of his inchanting dregs of error;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18.</note> having allured with great ſwelling words of vanity through the luſts of the fleſh, &amp;c. thoſe that were clean eſcaped from them; who live in error, while they promiſe them liberty, they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption, and how ſad it is for ſuch who have eſcaped the pollution of the world, through the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, to be again intangled and overcome: to ſuch the latter end is worſe then the beginning, and it had been better for them never to have known the wayes of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, then after they have known them, to turn from the holy commandment, like the dog to his vomit, and the Sow to her wallowing in the mire: if he had any ſenſe or feeling of the miſerable condition he hath drawn them into, if there were any knowledge of his own wayes, if himſelf were converted, ſure he could not ſuffer ſuch as theſe aforementioned to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in thoſe dangerous courſes; but ſhould labor to beat down the ſtrong holds of ſin and Satan, to unfold the myſteries of error, to ſtrengthen thoſe that are in the right-way, to bring back thoſe that are in the wrong, to undeceive thoſe that he hath ſeduced, which being often preſſed unto; and to ſuch from whom he hath formerly received the food for his belly, the rayment for his back, he hath refuſed to go to them; <hi>(becauſe he is the ſame man ſtill)</hi> wanting Chriſtian compaſſion to ſave others with fear, pulling them out of the fire that he hath led them into, ſetting himſelf moſt ungratefully againſt thoſe fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes who have offered moſt civilities to him, and from whom he hath received the greateſt ingagements; but he is ſo wedded to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35136:16"/>this preſent world, that he neglects friends, engagements, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities, and all things that may term him <hi>man,</hi> to enjoy it: mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney that he borrowed to buy a ſuite of cloaths in his neceſſity, he refuſes to pay in his plenty and abundance; returns of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity he ungratefully detains from the family at <hi>Bredwardine,</hi> and particularly from one of that family who hath ſtood up for him; which paſſage ſhall be the laſt in this Treatiſe, as being the moſt tranſcendent for villany and detraction of all; but yet it is no marvail, for ſince he denyes God, what fear is there left in him, when he ſolemnly invokes God by an oath? to bear falſe witneſs can be no trouble to his conſcience, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves neither a heaven nor an hell.</p>
            <p>The time (that you may perceive whether he be an altered and reformed man or no) was no longer ago then <hi>Septemb.</hi> 6. 1653. at <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> Captain <hi>Maſon</hi> having ſcandalouſly abuſed Captain <hi>Taylor</hi> by Articles exhibited againſt him in <hi>Haber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſhers</hi>-Hall, for refuſing to comply with him in the deceiving of his truſt, contrary to his oath, and not being able to prove any one, though in the attempt the witneſſes much forſwore themſelves, yet that there might be ſomewhat found in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, more then in the Articles; they the accuſers and privy proſecutors, having in writing drawn up the depoſitions, and worded them for the witneſſes; which <hi>Delamain</hi> not appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, becauſe they lacked ſomewhat of venom that he would have had inſerted againſt Captain <hi>Taylor,</hi> with his own hand mended and inſerted many words, which the witneſſes were to ſwear; cauſing many of them to own ſuch terms and words in their oaths, as they (poor people) could not underſtand; but that you may ſee he would not be behinde himſelf in ſuch an action as he puts others upon, have patience to read his oath, as it was by himſelf framed in writing, and returned to <hi>Haber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſhers</hi>-Hall, where it now lies atteſted and ſubſcribed with his own hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Delamain,</hi> ſworn and examined to the ſecond Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle againſt Captain <hi>Taylor,</hi> depoſeth and ſaith, that the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in the Garriſon of <hi>Hereford,</hi> upon Munday and Tueſday the 3. and 4. of <hi>January,</hi> 1652. were neceſſitated to keep all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35136:16"/>to their arms, by reaſon of a convention of Papiſts and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents then in the City of <hi>Hereford,</hi> occaſioned by a Muſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meeting, appointed by Captain <hi>Taylor:</hi> and whereas it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that he would have extenuated and mitigated the too too poſitive ſenſe, by thoſe croſs examinations upon interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories exhibited by Captain <hi>Taylor;</hi> being demanded whether he knew them Papiſts and Delinquents, and deſired to name them; it was beyond his ability, he could not name any of them, nor did he prove any of them to be Papiſts or Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents; but gives his paſſion vent, and diſchargeth ſuch a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of choller, ſwearing the ſecond time, <hi>That the Souldiery of the Garriſon of</hi> Hereford <hi>were neceſſitated to ſtand to their arms, upon occaſion of a Muſick-meeting of Papiſts and Delinquents, by Captain</hi> Taylors <hi>appointment:</hi> and further adds, (as under his own hand is in the office to be ſeen) <hi>that he doth not know of any of the honeſt party he doth either converſe or keep company with; (this is very large):</hi> but here he ſwears himſelf, the Governor, Captain <hi>Maſon,</hi> and the reſt of his own party knaves; for I am credibly informed, Captain <hi>Taylor</hi> kept not company more with any, then with them; and with them by much too much, as by their unhandſome undermining and juggling with him did appear. But I pray you obſerve the firſt part of his firſt oath: that the Souldiers of the Garriſon of <hi>Hereford</hi> were (on ſuch a time) <hi>neceſsitated</hi> to keep <hi>all</hi> to their arms, by reaſon of a <hi>convention of Papiſts and Delinquents, occaſioned by a muſick-meeting, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Captain</hi> Taylor: what credit he doth the Souldiers, to be affraid of a Muſick-meeting; ſurely the Souldiers of that Garriſon are <hi>fraughted</hi> with very unharmonious Souls, to be <hi>frighted</hi> with fiddles; (<hi>Delamain</hi> being Engenier, it may as well be, that the new rayles ſet up in Caſtle ſtreet, were to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſurpriſe by a <hi>Camiſado</hi> of Hobby-horſes.) and pray who were the company that put them into this terrible Alarum, and ſo much inſiſted upon affrightment? Do you think any of their own party could be there? truly you ſhall finde <hi>Mat. Price</hi> of the States Arms, Inholder, Gent. and <hi>G. Lynne,</hi> their own Croneys, participants in this dangerous enterprize, and to whom they were beholden for the ſtory, or elſe they had miſſed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35136:17"/>of an Article, and <hi>Delamain</hi> of matter to forſwear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf withal, beſides whom were but ten men and about ſix wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, moſt of them inhabitants of the City of <hi>Hereford;</hi> were not theſe dangerous people, and thoſe dangerous inſtruments, to ſurprize a Caſtle man'd with about 70. or 80. Souldiers, and of whom <hi>Delamain</hi> ſwears they were <hi>all</hi> neceſſitated to keep to their arms?
<note place="margin">They were in a good po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</note> yet one of them being brought to ſwear to this plot, (I think his name is <hi>James Vaughan,</hi> but it is <hi>Vaughan</hi>) tells you, he believes there was a deſign, becauſe he had much a do to eſcape caſheiring, for being abſent then; (it ſeemeth then it was not for kiſſing the Governors maide) ſo that <hi>all</hi> were not there <hi>(honeſt Delmain)</hi> but when it came to be ſtrictly ſearched into, neither the Souldiers, (for the greateſt part) nor Officers of the Caſtle ever knew of any ſuch meeting at Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Taylors;</hi> till ſuch time as half a year after, <hi>and above,</hi> the plot was found in the Articles againſt Captain <hi>Taylor,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome were ſo long after affrighted, and brought neer to that paſs, as the poor man that dyed the next day after he had paſſed a narrow plank that lay croſs a decayed Arch on <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi>-Bridge, upon the imagination of the danger he had eſcaped: Lieutenant <hi>Jenkins</hi> being at that time Deputy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, in the abſence of Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Rogers,</hi> did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, when he was ſummoned to depoſe this againſt Captain <hi>Taylor;</hi> (for ſuch a plot could not be known more plain to any, then to the then Governor) he called the Officers of the Garriſon together, and diligently enquired of them, whether they ever heard of any ſuch meeting at Captain <hi>Taylors?</hi> To which with one accord they anſwered, they never knew or heard of any ſuch meeting; and that they did not keep to their arms by reaſon of any convention at his houſe; which Lieutenant <hi>Jenkins</hi> did alſo declare for himſelf, by which he eſcaped the journey to <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> it being the place appointed, where, if he could or would, he ſhould have ſworn the plot, and this their ignorance, and not knowing then of the meeting, and their not ſtanding to their arms, by reaſon of the convention at Captain <hi>Taylors</hi> muſick, they will atteſt. Further, I have heard declared and aſcertained, that one of thoſe very nights, <hi>Delamain</hi> court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35136:17"/>Captain <hi>Taylor,</hi> in caſe there ſhould be any riſings in the Country, or ſtirs in the City, directing him a back way from his dwelling in the Pallace of <hi>Hereford,</hi> into the Caſtle; were I acquainted with Captain <hi>Taylor,</hi> I could have given you many more circumſtances, which I have heard of; but becauſe I would do nothing without a certain and ſure ground; nor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate his formerly-intended reſolutions, of expoſing the whole carriage of this buſineſs to a publick view; which would have been a great help to me in the management of this ſmall tract, and it may be a <hi>remora</hi> to the whole, (if he had done it effectually.) I have contented my ſelf with theſe few paſſages, in reſpect of the multitude of his Prevarications, becauſe that I have throughly informed my ſelf of the real truth of them, from honeſt Godly perſons of that County, who had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited certain collections of his enormities; and by my own ſearch into <hi>Haberdaſhers</hi>-Hall, at my own charge, of taking out orders and depoſitions.</p>
            <p>And now that you may ſee the horridneſs of <hi>Delamains</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing himſelf; the little account he makes of other mens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations; (having loſt his own) the improbability of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, the ſmall hopes of his amendment, his perverſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious and obdurate heart; as alſo Captain <hi>Taylors</hi> innocency adjuſted; and the good opinion and ſenſe after this charge againſt him, the Commiſſioners of <hi>Haberdaſhers</hi>-Hall had ſtill of him; be pleaſed to accept of the Order, as it lies there Regiſtred; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order">
                  <body>
                     <head>By the Commiſsioners for Compounding, &amp;c.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IN the Cauſe depending before us, upon a charge of miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor exhibited by Captain</hi> Maſon, <hi>againſt Captain</hi> Silas Taylor, <hi>one of the Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations in the County of</hi> Hereford; <hi>upon reading the ſeveral</hi> proofs <hi>ond</hi> depoſitions <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for and</hi> againſt <hi>the ſaid Captain</hi> Taylor; <hi>and upon deliberate hearing and debate thereof, and of what was offered and alledged
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35136:18"/>by the Counſel on both ſides.</hi>—Reſolved <hi>that we do</hi> not <hi>find the ſaid Captain</hi> Taylor <hi>to be</hi> guilty of the crimes contained in the aforeſaid charge: <hi>and do</hi> therefore acquit him of the ſame, <hi>And do Order that he be forthwith reſtored to his employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as a Commiſſioner for ſequeſtrations in the ſaid County of</hi> Hereford; <hi>and he is hereby enabled and impowered to act with the other Commiſſioners ſerving for the ſaid County, as formerly, in as full and ample manner, as if no order had been for ſuſpending him from the ſame.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>R. M. J. V. E. C. R. W.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>I hope by this you perceive him an egregious knave upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and with what a piece of peſtilence you have to deal: and by this let all his friends and fautors be warned of his friendſhip,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.</note> for, <hi>latet Anguis in herba;</hi> his <hi>throat is an open Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher, with his tongue he hath uſed deceit, and the poyſon of Aſps is under his lips;</hi> he makes no conſcience of his actions or ways neither to God or men; I need not further characterize him, theſe his actions, his words, his demeanors, and his practiſes are enough to render him in his own capacity, without any ſtrain or force, ſufficiently odious to the world.</p>
            <p>And now I challenge any one, that finds himſelf either in part, or in whole concerned in this Hiſtory, to diſprove the Truth of it: having received it from men truly religious, and of unblamable life and converſation, and out of ſuch undeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and unqueſſionable Records, as that the truth cannot ſuffer; yet before I conclude, let me humbly petition thoſe that are in Authority, to intereſt themſelves in the rooting out of ſuch prophaneneſs, blaſphemy, hereſie and hypocriſie, left hearing of theſe things, and not redreſſing of them, they draw on their own Souls the guilt of tolerating and connivence, if not of abetting ſuch Impoſtures as theſe are, to the undoing of many ſouls; it being the policy of that Grand Impoſtor, Satan, to work into a diſreliſh and diſlike of the truth, all ſuch as any wayes (though it be in bare profeſſion, without the root of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity) do ſet themſelves to worſhip God in a ſtricter and purer way then the common courſe of the world do: and to lay the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35136:18"/>heavieſt load of temptations upon ſuch that buckle themſelves to walk in the paths of Gods precepts:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>running the race with patience that is ſet before us, looking unto Jeſus</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Finiſher</hi> of our <hi>Faith;</hi> clothing our ſelves with <hi>circumſpection and vigilancy,</hi> continually to ſtand upon our guard,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.</note> leſt inſtead of <hi>Angels</hi> we <hi>entertain Devils,</hi> and inſtead of the <hi>myſterie of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> we participate of <hi>Myſterious Babylon, and ſo become per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers not only of her ſins, but of her plagues; her plagues that ſhall come upon her in one day, death, mourning, and famine, and ſhe ſhall be utterly burnt with fire, for ſtrong is the Lord God who judgeth her.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
